## Zhengxu Yu

 Ø zhengxuyu.github.io

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/yuzhengxu

https://github.com/zhengxuyu

#### Intro

Zhengxu Yu is currently a senior researcher at Alibaba Group. He obtained his Ph.D. from Zhejiang University, advised by Prof. Deng Cai and Prof. Xiaofei He. Previously, He obtained his Master's degree from University of Surrey, advised by Prof. H Lilian Tang.

His research interests focus on Machine Learning and Artificial General Intelligence, particularly in AI reasoning and decision-making models, alignment of AI decisions with human cognition, and stochastic modeling in dynamic systems.

His current research goal is to develop AI decision-making methods that can generate decisions which are practically applicable in the physical world and aligned with human cognition.

Zhengxu has published 11 research articles in top-tier international conferences and journals in the field of computer science, including IJCAI, AAAI, ECCV, etc.

#### **Education**

Zhejiang University, Ph.D. in Computer Science

Sept 2017 - Mar 2021

• Research Interests: Machine Learning, Computer Vision, Generative Model, Data Mining

University of Surrey, M.Sc. in Information Systems

Sept 2015 - Nov 2016

Research Interests: Machine Learning, Computer Vision, Data Mining

Jilin University, B.Sc. in Communication Engineering

Sept 2011 - June 2015

### Experience

#### Senior Algorithm Researcher, Alibaba Group – Hangzhou, China

Apr 2021 – present

- Developed Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Large Language Model (LLM) based models for reasoning and automatic decision making.
- Developed optimization methods to align AI decision-making models with human cognition.
- Developed stochastic modeling methods in dynamic system (e.g., urban traffic, dynamic engineering systems).
- Led cross-functional teams to deliver AI solutions and mentored research interns and junior developers.
- Collect customer needs to clarify goals and decompose complex scenarios into deliverable models in projects.

#### Research Intern, Damo Academy, Alibaba Group – Hangzhou, China

Jan 2018 - Apr 2021

- Proposed several multi-agent reinforcement learning methods to facilitate the coordination of multiple agents in cooperative and competitive scenarios.
- Proposed several optimization methods to improve the generalization ability of deep neural networks in computer vision tasks.
- Proposed a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) based synthetic data generating model for augmenting training data in computer vision tasks.
- Proposed several Deep Graph Neural Network (GNN) models for stochastic modeling tasks in dynamic systems.

#### **Projects**

### **Urban Device Automatic Operation System**

2023-present

- Built a large-scale system from scratch to manage massive urban IoT devices, which empowered device management, visual perception and automatic control.
- Developed a RL based model for automatic cooperative control in a dynamic system.
- Proposed a novel ReAct model for automatic task reasoning and decision-making.
- Designed & developed a data pipeline to gather human preference on AI decisions.

• Developed an RLHF based Alignment framework to align the policy model using human feedbacks.

#### **Urban Security Management System**

2022-2023

- Led a cross-functional team to develop a visual-based crowd monitoring system for accident prevention and risk mitigation at large urban events.
- Responsible for proof of concept development, designing the MLOps pipeline, managing client communications, and coordinating cross-functional teams.

#### **Urban Traffic Flow and Accident Risk Forecasting**

2021-2022

- Proposed a GNN-based model for stochastic traffic flow forecasting in urban areas.
- Developed a Multilayer Perceptron Network-based model to predict high-risk drivers from a dataset of 5 million samples, resulting in a 10% higher recall rate for actual accidents in a highly imbalanced dataset.

#### **Technologies**

Languages & Technologies: Python, PyTorch, Pandas, LangChain

Optimizing traffic efficiency via a reinforcement learning approach based on time allocation	2023
Cao, X., Jin, Z., <b>Yu, Z.</b> , Hua, X., Hu, Y., Qian Wei., Zhu K., Cai D., He, X.	
10.1007/s13042-023-01838-1 ☑ (International Journal of Machine Learning and Cybernetics)	
Progressive Transfer Learning	2022
<b>Yu, Z.</b> , Jin, Z., Wei, L., Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S.	
10.1109/TIP.2022.3141258 ☑ (IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP))	
Lidar point cloud guided monocular 3D object detection	2022
Peng,L., Liu,F., <b>Yu,Z.</b> , Yan,S., Deng,D., Yang,Z., Liu,H., Cai,D.	
10.1007/978-3-031-19769-7-8 🗹 (ECCV)	
COP: customized correlation-based filter level pruning method for deep CNN compression	2021
Wang, W., <b>Yu, Z.</b> , Fu, C., Cai, D., He, X	
10.1109/TIP.2022.3141258 <b>☑</b> (Neurocomputing)	
Urban Traffic Light Control via Active Multi-agent Communication and Supply-Demand Modeling	2021
Guo, X.+, <b>Yu, Z.+</b> , Wang, P., Jin, Z., Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S., ( <b>+</b> Co-first author)	
10.1109/TKDE.2021.3130258 ☑ (IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering)	
Apparel-invariant Feature Learning for Person Re-identification	2021
<b>Yu, Z.</b> , Zhao, Y., Hong, B., Jin, Z., Huang, J., Cai, D., Hua, X.S.	
10.1109/TMM.2021.3119133 ☑ (IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP))	
MaCAR: Urban Traffic Light Control via Active Multi-agent Communication and Ac- tion Rectification	2020
<b>Yu, Z.</b> , Liang, S., Wei, L., Jin, Z., Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S.	
10.24963/IJCAI.2020/345 <b>☑</b> (IJCAI)	
PI-RCNN: An efficient multi-sensor 3D object detector with point-based attentive cont-conv fusion module	2020
Xie, L., Xiang, C., <b>Yu, Z.</b> , Xu, G., Yang, Z., Cai, D., He, X.	
10.1609/aaai.v34i07.6933 <b>☑ (AAAI)</b>	
SIF: Self-Inspirited Feature Learning for Person Re-Identification	2020
Wei, L., Wei, Z., Jin, Z., <b>Yu, Z.</b> , Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S.	

# 10.1109/TIP.2020.2975712 🗹 (IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)) Progressive Transfer Learning for Person Re-identification 2019 Yu, Z., Jin, Z., Wei, L., Guo, J., Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S. 10.24963/ijcai.2019/586 🗹 (IJCAI-2019) Dual Graph for Traffic Forecasting Wei, L.+, Yu, Z.+, Jin, Z., Xie, L., Huang, J., Cai, D., He, X., Hua, X.S., (+Co-first author) 10.1109/ACCESS.2019.2958380 🗹 (IEEE ACCESS)